Stoneham, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1728-1889.
Congregational Library & Archives
Stoneham, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1728-1889.
RG5190
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
The town of Stoneham was incorporated in 1725. A vote in 1726 provided for the building of a meetinghouse and the First Congregational Church was organized in 1729. The first pastor was Rev. James Osgood who was ordained in September 1729. Rev. John Cleaveland was pastor from 1785 until an ecclesiastical council dissolved his relationship with the town in 1894. The second meeting house was constructed in 1803 and the third in 1840. This collection contains the early records the Church. Included are church records of meeting minutes, vital statistics, parish and financial records, and ministerial records.
First Congregational Church (Stoneham, Mass.)
Osgood, James, 1705-1746
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Collection gifted to the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church in Stoneham, June 2014; Accession: 2014-39.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The town of Stoneham, previously known as Charlestown End, was incorporated in 1725. A vote in 1726 provided for the building of a 1,440-square-foot meetinghouse however the First Congregational Church itself was not organized until July 1729, with thirteen founding members, when the first church covenant was read and adopted. The first pastor was Rev. James Osgood, a 24 year old Harvard graduate from Salem, who was called in October 1728, and ordained in September 1729. Osgood served until his death in 1746 and was replaced by John Carnes, who was dismissed from his position in 1757. John Searl succeeded Carnes in 1758, followed by the ordination of John Cleaveland Jr. in 1785.
Rev. John Cleaveland Jr. was the son of Rev. John Cleveland of Essex, a separatist minister who served as a chaplain in the French and Indian War and the American Revolution. Cleaveland Jr., unable to pay for a college education, was instead taught by his father. His pastorate at Stoneham was his first ministry. Cleaveland's ministry began amicably. With the opening of the Stoneham Circulating Library, which was kept at the parsonage, Cleaveland became the town's first librarian. Cleaveland's relationship with the church's members remained favorable until the passing of his wife in 1793. Following his wife's death, Cleaveland married Elizabeth Evans, his housekeeper. The reaction to this marriage was negative; at various times Cleaveland found the door to the meeting house nailed shut, the seat of the pulpit covered in tar, and the tail of his horse cut off. While the church itself supported Cleaveland, the town consistently did not, refusing to raise his salary and going so far as to shutter the meeting house so that public worship could not be held there. An ecclesiastical council called late September 1794 dissolved Cleaveland's relationship with the town and church.
Several pastors were called after Cleaveland, and in 1803 the town voted for the construction of a new, larger, meetinghouse. A bell for the new meetinghouse's belfry was purchased in 1810 with money raised through subscription, and a Sabbath-school was established in 1816. The second meetinghouse burned to the ground in 1840. That same year, at the cost of $5,500, the third, and final, meeting house was constructed. An example of Greek Revival architecture, the third meeting house was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 1984.
The First Congregational Church in Stoneham, UCC, continues to serve the local community today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the early records of First Congregational Church in Stoneham, Massachusetts. Included in this collection are church records of meeting minutes, vital statistics, and membership rolls; parish and financial records, including salary and capital expenses; and documents created by ministers who served the church, including commonplace and account books from James Osgood, and sermons from an unnamed minister, most likely John Stevens who served in both Stoneham and Haverhill. Of particular note is the Osgood family's account book which contains not only the accounts of Rev. James Osgood, but also records of his wife, Sarah Osgood's, household and other expenses.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series. Within each series, the materials have been organized chronologically.
Series 1: Church records, 1728-1840
Series 2: Parish and Financial records, 1803-1889
Series 3: Ministerial records, 1728-1827
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
Stevens, Judge. Historical Sketch of the First Congregational Church in Stoneham. Stoneham, 1929. 17.11.1 S75.2 FirCC
Account books.; Baptism and church membership.; Baptismal records.; Church records and registers.; Clergy -- Appointment, call, and election.; Clergy -- Relocation.; Excommunication.; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Pews and pew rights.; Ordination.; Ordination sermons -- Early works to 1800.; Sermons, American.; Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.; Cleaveland, John, 1749-1815; First Congregational Church (Stoneham, Mass.); Osgood, James, 1705-1746; Stoneham (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church records, 1728 1840; 1728-1840; 6 Files; (3 volumes, 3 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the early church records of First Congregational Church in Stoneham, Massachusetts. Included in this series are records of church meeting minutes, marriage records, baptismal records, and statements of faith.
  - Church records, 1728 1798; 1728-1798 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Digital Copies
    These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This volume contains church meeting minutes, including record of the call to Osgood as settled pastor, articles of faith, records of church discipline, including censure, membership records, baptismal records, and marriage records.
  - Statement of faith by John H. Stevens, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Resolution, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1798 1840; 1798-1840 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    This volume contains church meeting minutes, membership records, baptismal records, ecclesiastical council notes, and lists of financial donations.
  - Marriage record, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Separated Materials
    These materials were separated from the volume "Marriage records, 1828-1831" to be housed separately.
  - Marriage records, 1828 1831; 1828-1831 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This volume is comprised of marriage, death, and baptism records. There is also a record of a bequest to the church and congregation.
- Parish and Financial records, 1803 1889; 1803-1889; 7 Files; (6 volumes, 1 folder)
  This series contains the financial records of First Congregational Church in Stoneham, Massachusetts. These records include pew deeds and pew tax records, meeting minutes, records pertaining to the replacement of the church bell and the purchase and installation of a new furnace, and committee reports.
  - Parish records, 1803 1876; 1803-1876 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    This volume contains quit-claim deeds for pews, financial record, minutes, other pew deeds, and bills of sale. Of particular note is a non-contemporaneous index inserted into the front of the volume.
  - Records of the Treasurer, 1827 1856; 1827-1856 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    This volume is comprised of financial records pertaining to the parish treasury. Records include names of recipients and the purpose of the payment as well as date.
  - Parish records, 1827 1856; 1827-1856 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    This volume contains parish meeting minutes and records of votes, committee reports, information on the replacement of the church bell, and records pertaining to the purchase and installation of a furnace.
  - Financial records, 1827 1872; 1827-1872 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    This volume includes financial records such as records of taxes for the support of the parish and pew taxes.
  - Financial records, 1828 1868; 1828-1868 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    This volume is comprised primarily of financial records of the church and its subscribers. Also included are committee reports and notes on church finances, including an assessment and mortgage for the parsonage.
  - Deeds to Pews, 1841 1867; 1841-1867 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Parish records, 1856 1899; 1856-1889 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    This volume is comprised of meeting minutes, meeting warrants, pew sale records, financial records, officer and member lists, admissions, dismissions, and correspondence. Also included is a Rev. William Batt's resignation and Rev. D. Augustine's acceptance of the position as replacement, as well as records of his installation. The records end with Rev. Augustine's dismission.
- Ministerial records, 1728 1827; 1728-1827; 5 Files; (3 volumes, 2 folders)
  This series contains personal account books, records, sermons, and realia created and kept by ministers of First Congregational Church in Stoneham, Massachusetts.
  - James Osgood's book, 1728 1731; 1728-1731 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    Kept by James Osgood, First Congregatinal Church's first pastor, this book contains pages of "remarkable things," accounts of salary Osgood recieved in Salisbury, a list of moneys paid to creditors, sermon notes, and books received by Osgood. The volume also contains birth/baptismal records kept in a different hand.
  - James Osgood's neckwear, 1729 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Osgood account book, 1740 1796; 1740-1796 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    This is an account book of the Osgood family, including James Osgood's expenses and Sarah Osgood's expenses, most of the household expenses for foodstuffs (including rum, chocolate, and butchery services) and clothing goods (including sewing supplies, silk, whale bone, and stays).
  - Ordination sermon, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sermons, 1798 1827; 1798-1827 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    These are 14 sets of sermon notes. Each sermon is handwritten in a separate pamphlet. The sermons are unattributed with multiple dates and locations, indicating reuse by the pastor. Rev. John Stevens may have been the author of some or all of these sermons.
    List of Sermons
    Psalm 116:7 - first preached July 1, 1798
    Luke 24:30 - first preached August 14, 1803
    Isaiah 8:17 - first preached April 29, 1804
    Sermon with no citation - first preached January 4, 1807
    Zachariah 1:5 - first preached February 12, 1809
    Acts 9:6 - first preached December 12, 1809
    1 Peter 5:7 - first preached October 3, 1813
    Philippians 4:8 - first preached May 23, 1819
    Ecclesiastes 8:5 - first preached January 2, 1820
    2 Peter 1:1 - first preached July 1, 1821
    Philippians 1:23 - first preached December 7, 1823
    Deuteronomy 32:5-6 - first preached April 1, 1824
    Jeremiah 21:8 - first preached January 22, 1826
    Ezekiel 37:11-13 - first preached December 28, 1827